Flex: Compose your Application

After reading the first part of this tutorial, you have decided that Symfony was worth another 10 minutes. Great choice! In this second part, you’ll learn about Symfony Flex: the amazing tool that makes adding new features as simple as running one command. It’s also the reason why Symfony is ideal for a small micro-service or a huge application. Curious? Perfect!

Symfony: Start Micro!

Unless you’re building a pure API (more on that soon!), you’ll probably want to render HTML. To do that, you’ll use Twig [https://twig.symfony.com/]. Twig is a flexible, fast, and secure template engine for PHP. It makes your templates more readable and concise; it also makes them more friendly for web designers.

Is Twig already installed in our application? Actually, not yet! And that’s great! When you start a new Symfony project, it’s small: only the most critical dependencies are included in your composer.json file:

1
2
3
4
5
6
7

|

"require": {
    "...",
    "symfony/console": "^4.1",
    "symfony/flex": "^1.0",
    "symfony/framework-bundle": "^4.1",
    "symfony/yaml": "^4.1"
}

This makes Symfony different than any other PHP framework! Instead of starting with a bulky app with every possible feature you might ever need, a Symfony app is small, simple and fast. And you’re in total control of what you add.

Flex Recipes and Aliases

So how can we install and configure Twig? By running one single command:

1

|

$ composer require twig

Two very interesting things happen behind the scenes thanks to Symfony Flex: a Composer plugin that is already installed in our project.

First, twig is not the name of a Composer package: it’s a Flex alias that points to symfony/twig-bundle. Flex resolves that alias for Composer.

And second, Flex installs a recipe for symfony/twig-bundle. What’s a recipe? It’s a way for a library to automatically configure itself by adding and modifying files. Thanks to recipes, adding features is seamless and automated: install a package and you’re done!

You can find a full list of recipes and aliases by going to https://flex.symfony.com.

What did this recipe do? In addition to automatically enabling the feature in config/bundles.php, it added 3 things:

config/packages/twig.yaml

A configuration file that sets up Twig with sensible defaults.

config/packages/test/twig.yaml

A configuration file that changes some Twig options when running tests.

templates/

This is the directory where template files will live. The recipe also added a base.html.twig layout file.

Twig: Rendering a Template

Thanks to Flex, after one command, you can start using Twig immediately:

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21
22

|

<?php
// src/Controller/DefaultController.php
namespace App\Controller;

use Symfony\Component\Routing\Annotation\Route;
- use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Response;
+ use Symfony\Bundle\FrameworkBundle\Controller\AbstractController;

-class DefaultController
+class DefaultController extends AbstractController
 {
     /**
      * @Route("/hello/{name}")
      */
     public function index($name)
     {
-        return new Response("Hello $name!");
+        return $this->render('default/index.html.twig', [
+            'name' => $name,
+        ]);
     }
}

By extending AbstractController, you now have access to a number of shortcut methods and tools, like render(). Create the new template:

1
2

|

{# templates/default/index.html.twig #}
<h1>Hello {{ name }}</h1>

That’s it! The {{ name }} syntax will print the name variable that’s passed in from the controller. If you’re new to Twig, welcome! You’ll learn more about its syntax and power later.

But, right now, the page only contains the h1 tag. To give it an HTML layout, extend base.html.twig:

1
2
3
4
5
6

|

{# templates/default/index.html.twig #}
{% extends 'base.html.twig' %}

{% block body %}
    <h1>Hello {{ name }}</h1>
{% endblock %}

This is called template inheritance: our page now inherits the HTML structure from base.html.twig.

Profiler: Debugging Paradise

One of the coolest features of Symfony isn’t even installed yet! Let’s fix that:

1

|

$ composer require profiler

Yes! This is another alias! And Flex also installs another recipe, which automates the configuration of Symfony’s Profiler. What’s the result? Refresh!

See that black bar on the bottom? That’s the web debug toolbar, and it’s your new best friend. By hovering over each icon, you can get information about what controller was executed, performance information, cache hits & misses and a lot more. Click any icon to go into the profiler where you have even more detailed debugging and performance data!

Oh, and as you install more libraries, you’ll get more tools (like a web debug toolbar icon that shows database queries).

You can now directly use the profiler because it configured itself thanks to the recipe. What else can we install?

Rich API Support

Are you building an API? You can already return JSON from any controller:

<?php
// src/Controller/DefaultController.php
namespace App\Controller;

use Symfony\Bundle\FrameworkBundle\Controller\AbstractController;
use Symfony\Component\Routing\Annotation\Route;

class DefaultController extends AbstractController
{
    // ...

    /**
     * @Route("/api/hello/{name}")
     */
    public function apiExample($name)
    {
        return $this->json([
            'name' => $name,
            'symfony' => 'rocks',
        ]);
    }
}

But for a truly rich API, try installing API Platform [https://api-platform.com/]:

1

|

$ composer require api

This is an alias to api-platform/api-pack Symfony pack, which has dependencies on several other packages, like Symfony’s Validator and Security components, as well as the Doctrine ORM. In fact, Flex installed 5 recipes!

But like usual, we can immediately start using the new library. Want to create a rich API for a product table? Create a Product entity and give it the @ApiResource() annotation:

<?php
// src/Entity/Product.php
namespace App\Entity;

use ApiPlatform\Core\Annotation\ApiResource;
use Doctrine\ORM\Mapping as ORM;

/**
 * @ORM\Entity()
 * @ApiResource()
 */
class Product
{
    /**
     * @ORM\Id
     * @ORM\GeneratedValue(strategy="AUTO")
     * @ORM\Column(type="integer")
     */
    private $id;

    /**
     * @ORM\Column(type="string")
     */
    private $name;

    /**
     * @ORM\Column(type="int")
     */
    private $price;

    // ...
}

Done! You now have endpoints to list, add, update and delete products! Don’t believe me? List your routes by running:

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11
12

|

$ php bin/console debug:router

------------------------------ -------- -------------------------------------
 Name                           Method   Path
------------------------------ -------- -------------------------------------
 api_products_get_collection    GET      /api/products.{_format}
 api_products_post_collection   POST     /api/products.{_format}
 api_products_get_item          GET      /api/products/{id}.{_format}
 api_products_put_item          PUT      /api/products/{id}.{_format}
 api_products_delete_item       DELETE   /api/products/{id}.{_format}
 ...
------------------------------ -------- -------------------------------------

Removing Recipes

Not convinced yet? No problem: remove the library:

1

|

$ composer remove api

Flex will uninstall the recipes: removing files and un-doing changes to put your app back in its original state. Experiment without worry.

More Features, Architecture and Speed

I hope you’re as excited about Flex as I am! But we still have one more chapter, and it’s the most important yet. I want to show you how Symfony empowers you to quickly build features without sacrificing code quality or performance. It’s all about the service container, and it’s Symfony’s super power. Read on: about The Architecture.

The Architecture

You are my hero! Who would have thought that you would still be here after the first two parts? Your efforts will be well-rewarded soon. The first two parts didn’t look too deeply at the architecture of the framework. Because it makes Symfony stand apart from the framework crowd, let’s dive into the architecture now.

Add Logging

A new Symfony app is micro: it’s basically just a routing & controller system. But thanks to Flex, installing more features is simple.

Want a logging system? No problem:

1

|

$ composer require logger

This installs and configures (via a recipe) the powerful Monolog [https://github.com/Seldaek/monolog] library. To use the logger in a controller, add a new argument type-hinted with LoggerInterface:

<?php
// src/Controller/DefaultController.php
namespace App\Controller;

use Psr\Log\LoggerInterface;
use Symfony\Bundle\FrameworkBundle\Controller\AbstractController;
use Symfony\Component\Routing\Annotation\Route;

class DefaultController extends AbstractController
{
    /**
     * @Route("/hello/{name}")
     */
    public function index($name, LoggerInterface $logger)
    {
        $logger->info("Saying hello to $name!");

        // ...
    }
}

That’s it! The new log message will be written to var/log/dev.log. The log file path or even a different method of logging can be configured by updating one of the config files added by the recipe.

Services & Autowiring

But wait! Something very cool just happened. Symfony read the LoggerInterface type-hint and automatically figured out that it should pass us the Logger object! This is called autowiring.

Every bit of work that’s done in a Symfony app is done by an object: the Logger object logs things and the Twig object renders templates. These objects are called services and they are tools that help you build rich features.

To make life awesome, you can ask Symfony to pass you a service by using a type-hint. What other possible classes or interfaces could you use? Find out by running:

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17

|

$ php bin/console debug:autowiring

  # this is just a *small* sample of the output...

  Describes a logger instance.
  Psr\Log\LoggerInterface (monolog.logger)

  Request stack that controls the lifecycle of requests.
  Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\RequestStack (request_stack)

  Interface for the session.
  Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Session\SessionInterface (session)

  RouterInterface is the interface that all Router classes must implement.
  Symfony\Component\Routing\RouterInterface (router.default)

  [...]

This is just a short summary of the full list! And as you add more packages, this list of tools will grow!

Creating Services

To keep your code organized, you can even create your own services! Suppose you want to generate a random greeting (e.g. “Hello”, “Yo”, etc). Instead of putting this code directly in your controller, create a new class:

<?php
// src/GreetingGenerator.php
namespace App;

class GreetingGenerator
{
    public function getRandomGreeting()
    {
        $greetings = ['Hey', 'Yo', 'Aloha'];
        $greeting = $greetings[array_rand($greetings)];

        return $greeting;
    }
}

Great! You can use this immediately in your controller:

<?php
// src/Controller/DefaultController.php
namespace App\Controller;

use App\GreetingGenerator;
use Psr\Log\LoggerInterface;
use Symfony\Bundle\FrameworkBundle\Controller\AbstractController;
use Symfony\Component\Routing\Annotation\Route;

class DefaultController extends AbstractController
{
    /**
     * @Route("/hello/{name}")
     */
    public function index($name, LoggerInterface $logger, GreetingGenerator $generator)
    {
        $greeting = $generator->getRandomGreeting();

        $logger->info("Saying $greeting to $name!");

        // ...
    }
}

That’s it! Symfony will instantiate the GreetingGenerator automatically and pass it as an argument. But, could we also move the logger logic to GreetingGenerator? Yes! You can use autowiring inside a service to access other services. The only difference is that it’s done in the constructor:

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21
22

|

<?php
// src/GreetingGenerator.php
+ use Psr\Log\LoggerInterface;

class GreetingGenerator
{
+     private $logger;
+
+     public function __construct(LoggerInterface $logger)
+     {
+         $this->logger = $logger;
+     }

    public function getRandomGreeting()
    {
        // ...

+        $this->logger->info('Using the greeting: '.$greeting);

         return $greeting;
    }
}

Yes! This works too: no configuration, no time wasted. Keep coding!

Twig Extension & Autoconfiguration

Thanks to Symfony’s service handling, you can extend Symfony in many ways, like by creating an event subscriber or a security voter for complex authorization rules. Let’s add a new filter to Twig called greet. How? Create a class that extends AbstractExtension:

<?php
// src/Twig/GreetExtension.php
namespace App\Twig;

use App\GreetingGenerator;
use Twig\Extension\AbstractExtension;
use Twig\TwigFilter;

class GreetExtension extends AbstractExtension
{
    private $greetingGenerator;

    public function __construct(GreetingGenerator $greetingGenerator)
    {
        $this->greetingGenerator = $greetingGenerator;
    }

    public function getFilters()
    {
        return [
            new TwigFilter('greet', [$this, 'greetUser']),
        ];
    }

    public function greetUser($name)
    {
        $greeting =  $this->greetingGenerator->getRandomGreeting();

        return "$greeting $name!";
    }
}

After creating just one file, you can use this immediately:

1
2
3

|

{# templates/default/index.html.twig #}
{# Will print something like "Hey Symfony!" #}
<h1>{{ name|greet }}</h1>

How does this work? Symfony notices that your class extends AbstractExtension and so automatically registers it as a Twig extension. This is called autoconfiguration, and it works for many many things. Create a class and then extend a base class (or implement an interface). Symfony takes care of the rest.

Blazing Speed: The Cached Container

After seeing how much Symfony handles automatically, you might be wondering: “Doesn’t this hurt performance?” Actually, no! Symfony is blazing fast.

How is that possible? The service system is managed by a very important object called the “container”. Most frameworks have a container, but Symfony’s is unique because it’s cached. When you loaded your first page, all of the service information was compiled and saved. This means that the autowiring and autoconfiguration features add no overhead! It also means that you get great errors: Symfony inspects and validates everything when the container is built.

Now you might be wondering what happens when you update a file and the cache needs to rebuild? I like your thinking! It’s smart enough to rebuild on the next page load. But that’s really the topic of the next section.

Development Versus Production: Environments

One of a framework’s main jobs is to make debugging easy! And our app is full of great tools for this: the web debug toolbar displays at the bottom of the page, errors are big, beautiful & explicit, and any configuration cache is automatically rebuilt whenever needed.

But what about when you deploy to production? We will need to hide those tools and optimize for speed!

This is solved by Symfony’s environment system and there are three: dev, prod and test. Based on the environment, Symfony loads different files in the config/ directory:

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19

|

config/
├─ services.yaml
├─ ...
└─ packages/
    ├─ framework.yaml
    ├─ ...
    ├─ **dev/**
        ├─ monolog.yaml
        └─ ...
    ├─ **prod/**
        └─ monolog.yaml
    └─ **test/**
        ├─ framework.yaml
        └─ ...
└─ routes/
    ├─ annotations.yaml
    └─ **dev/**
        ├─ twig.yaml
        └─ web_profiler.yaml

This is a powerful idea: by changing one piece of configuration (the environment), your app is transformed from a debugging-friendly experience to one that’s optimized for speed.

Oh, how do you change the environment? Change the APP_ENV environment variable from dev to prod:

1
2
3

|

# .env
- APP_ENV=dev
+ APP_ENV=prod

But I want to talk more about environment variables next. Change the value back to dev: debugging tools are great when you’re working locally.

Environment Variables

Every app contains configuration that’s different on each server - like database connection information or passwords. How should these be stored? In files? Or some other way?

Symfony follows the industry best practice by storing server-based configuration as environment variables. This means that Symfony works perfectly with Platform as a Service (PaaS) deployment systems as well as Docker.

But setting environment variables while developing can be a pain. That’s why your app automatically loads a .env file. The keys in this file then become environment variables and are read by your app:

1
2
3
4
5

|

# .env
###> symfony/framework-bundle ###
APP_ENV=dev
APP_SECRET=cc86c7ca937636d5ddf1b754beb22a10
###< symfony/framework-bundle ###

At first, the file doesn’t contain much. But as your app grows, you’ll add more configuration as you need it. But, actually, it gets much more interesting! Suppose your app needs a database ORM. Let’s install the Doctrine ORM:

1

|

$ composer require doctrine

Thanks to a new recipe installed by Flex, look at the .env file again:

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9

|

###> symfony/framework-bundle ###
APP_ENV=dev
APP_SECRET=cc86c7ca937636d5ddf1b754beb22a10
###< symfony/framework-bundle ###

+ ###> doctrine/doctrine-bundle ###
+ # ...
+ DATABASE_URL=mysql://db_user:db_password@127.0.0.1:3306/db_name
+ ###< doctrine/doctrine-bundle ###

The new DATABASE_URL environment variable was added automatically and is already referenced by the new doctrine.yaml configuration file. By combining environment variables and Flex, you’re using industry best practices without any extra effort.

Keep Going!

Call me crazy, but after reading this part, you should be comfortable with the most important parts of Symfony. Everything in Symfony is designed to get out of your way so you can keep coding and adding features, all with the speed and quality you demand.

That’s all for the quick tour. From authentication, to forms, to caching, there is so much more to discover. Ready to dig into these topics now? Look no further - go to the official Symfony Documentation and pick any guide you want.